<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2002-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
	<header>
		<title>Authoring and Live Mode</title>
	</header>
	<body>

		<section>
			<title>Introduction</title>
			
			<p>Lenya has two modes it can run in:</p>
			<ul>
			<li>In Authoring mode it is a web application enabling editors
			to interactively manipulate the structure as well as the content of a publication.</li>
			<li>In Live mode it will render a publication as a website.</li>
			</ul>
			
			<section>
			
				<title>Authoring Mode</title>
				
				<p>Authoring a publication involves a number of different tasks:</p>
				<ul>
				<li>Creating new documents</li>
				<li>Moving documents around in the sitetree</li>
				<li>Editing a document's content</li>
				<li>Editing a document's metadata</li>
				</ul>
				
				<p>but also:</p>
				
				<ul>
				<li>Editing a publication's metadata</li>
				<li>Managing the resource types and editors available</li>
				<li>Maintaining access control policies both for editing and for the live publication</li>
				</ul>
				
				<p>Transactions that manipulate the publication are implemented through usecases, using the
				Usecase Framework. There are for example usecases that:</p>
				
				<ul>
				<li>Create a new document</li>
				<li>Delete a document</li>
				<li>Edit a document's metadata</li>
				<li>Call an editor to edit the document's content</li>
				</ul>

			</section>

			<section>
				
				<title>Live Mode</title>
				
				<p>The Live Mode is all about presenting a publication to the viewer.</p>
				<p>HTTP requests are passed through a Cocoon sitemap which will then
				use the appropriate generators, transformers and serializers which will
				return a page to the browser in reply to the request.</p>
				
				<section>
					<title>Serving a Lenya publication with plain Cocoon only?</title>
					<p>The fact that Live Mode is all about serving pages controlled by
					a sitemap often raises the question if it was possible to serve a 
					publication that has been edited with Lenya from a plain Cocoon instance.</p>
					<p>Sometimes this might be a requirement if the production site offers Cocoon
					hosting but not Lenya hosting for example. Also some architects feel better
					if the editor portion is not at all installed on an outside facing prodction
					server.</p>
					<p>While it would theoretically be possible, at the time of writing a Lenya
					publication will need Lenya even for Live mode. The reason is that the sitemaps
					use some custom Cocoon components that are part of Lenya, such as the PageEnvelope
					input module for example.</p>
					<p>Again, it would be possible to extract these components from Lenya and package
					them with a plain instance of Cocoon to achive to goal of having a "Live mode only"
					version of Lenya that will not allow any editing. Yet this work has not yet been done.</p>
				</section>
				
			</section>
			
		</section>	
		
	</body>
</document>
