<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
      xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
      xmlns:lenya="http://apache.org/cocoon/lenya/page-envelope/1.0"
>
  <head>
    <title>Related Projects</title>
  </head>
  <body>  
  
    <h2>Related Projects</h2>
    <p>
        This list is featuring projects which are closely related to Apache Lenya. 
        Open Source Content Management Systems overviews can be found at 
        <a href="http://www.oscom.org">oscom.org</a> or <a href="http://www.cmsinfo.org">cmsinfo.org</a>. 
        More information on Cocoon-based projects can be found at
        <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/link/projects.html">http://cocoon.apache.org/link/projects.html</a>.
    </p>
    <div class="column1of2"> 
      <h3>Cocoon</h3>
      <p>Apache Cocoon is an XML publishing framework that raises the usage of XML and XSLT
      technologies for server applications to a new level. Designed for performance and
      scalability around pipelined SAX processing, Cocoon offers a flexible environment
      based on a separation of concerns between content, logic, and style. To top this all
      off, Cocoons centralized configuration system and sophisticated caching help you to
      create, deploy, and maintain rock-solid XML server applications.</p>
      <p><a href="http://cocoon.apache.org">http://cocoon.apache.org</a></p>

      <h3>Slide</h3>
      <p>The Slide project main module is a Content Management and Integration System, which
      can be seen as a low-level content management framework. Conceptually, it provides
      a hierarchical organization of binary content which can be stored into arbitrary,
      heterogenous, distributed data stores. In addition, Slide integrates security, locking,
      versioning, as well as many other services.</p>
      <p><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/slide/">http://jakarta.apache.org/slide/</a></p>
    </div>

    <div class="column2of2">
      <h3>Jackrabbit</h3>
      <p>The Jackrabbit Project has been formed to develop an open source implementation of the 
      Content Repository for Java Technology API (JCR), being specified within the Java Community 
      Process as JSR-170.</p>
      <p><a href="http://incubator.apache.org/jackrabbit/">http://incubator.apache.org/jackrabbit/</a></p>

      <h3>Forrest</h3>
      <p>Apache Forrest is an XML standards-oriented documentation framework based on Apache Cocoon, 
      providing XSLT stylesheets and schemas, images and other resources. Forrest uses these to render 
      the XML source content into a website via command-line, robot, or a dynamic web application.</p>
      <p><a href="http://forrest.apache.org/">http://forrest.apache.org/</a></p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <br class="clear" />
      <br /><br />
      <br /><br />
      <br /><br />
      <br /><br />
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
