<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>Basic Terms</title>
		<version/>
		<type/>
		<authors>
			<person name="Andreas Hartmann" email="andreas@apache.org"/>
		</authors>
	</header>

  <body>
	
<section>
	<title>Role</title>
	<p><em>Role</em>s are the connection between access control and CMS functionality. On
		the access control side, you assign <em>Role</em>s to users, IP address ranges and
		groups at certain URL spaces. On the CMS side, you define which <em>Role</em>s are
		needed to execute certain usecases and workflow transitions. If the client has a certain
		<em>Role</em>, this means he is allowed to do something.</p>
	<p>Each <em>Role</em> has a unique name. Role names can be arbitrary strings. Examples are</p>
	<ul>
		<li>author</li>
		<li>reviewer</li>
		<li>admin</li>
	</ul>
	<p>Another common approach and useful is to use verbs as role names:</p>
	<ul>
		<li>edit</li>
		<li>review</li>
		<li>administrate</li>
	</ul>
</section>


<section>
	<title>Identifiable</title>
	<p>An <em>Identifiable</em> is a characteristic of the client that can be identified.
		Every <em>Identifiable</em> is <em>Accreditable</em>. Lenya currently supports the following
		<em>Identifiable</em>s:</p>
	<ul>
		<li>users</li>
		<li>machines</li>
		<li>the world (this idenitifiable is assigned to every client that tries to
			access the system)</li>
	</ul>
</section>


<section><title>Identity</title>
	<p>An <em>Identity</em> is the collection of all <em>Identifiable</em>s
	  that have access to the
		system in the current session. The <em>Identity</em> always contains the world and
		the machine that produced the request. If you logged in, the user is also
		contained in the <em>Identity</em>.</p>
	<p>For instance, if you log in from the machine 192.168.0.16 as the user john,
		the <em>Identity</em> of the client contains</p>
  <ul>
    <li>the machine 192.168.0.16,</li>
    <li>the user john</li>, and
    <li>the world.</li>
  </ul>
</section>


<section><title>Accreditable</title>
  <p>An <em>Accreditable</em> can be accredited with <em>Role</em>s in <em>Policies</em>.
	Lenya currently supports the following <em>Accreditable</em>s:</p>
	<ul>
		<li>users</li>
		<li>machines (accredition not implemented, use IP ranges instead)</li>
		<li>IP address ranges</li>
		<li>the world</li>
		<li>groups</li>
	</ul>
</section>


<section>
	<title>Credential</title>
	<p>A <em>Credential</em> assigns a set of <em>Role</em>s to an <em>Accreditable</em>, e.g.:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><code>news_editors: editor, reviewer</code><br/> means "The group 
			<code>news_editors</code> has the <em>Role</em>s <code>editor</code> and <code>
			reviewer</code>."</li>
	</ul>
</section>


<section>
	<title>Policy</title>
	<p>A <em>Policy</em> defines a set of <em>Credential</em>s for a certain URL. It has the
		responsibility to return all <em>Role</em>s of an <em>Accreditable</em> at a certain URL.</p>
	<p>If for instance the <em>Policy</em> for the URL /tv/news contains the <em>Credential</em>s</p>
	<ul>
		<li>
			<code>news_editors: editor, reviewer</code>
		</li>
		<li>
			<code>john: admin</code>
		</li>
		<li>
			<code>192.168.0.72: visitor</code>
		</li>
	</ul>
	<p>and user <code>john</code> belongs to the group <code>news_editors</code> 
		and has logged in from the machine <code>192.168.0.72</code>, the <em>Policy</em>
		returns the <em>Role</em>s <code>editor, reviewer, admin, visitor</code> for the
		<em>Accreditable</em> <code>john</code>.</p>
	<p>A <em>Policy</em> may not contain invalid <em>Accreditable</em>s.
	  E.g., if a user is deleted
		and another user with the same ID is created, he may not get the same
		privileges as the former one.</p>
</section>

  </body>
</document>
