<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!-- $Id: index.xml 55543 2004-10-26 00:14:59Z gregor $ -->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Part 1: Understanding Lenya</title>
  </header>
    <body>
        <p>In this first installment in a series of articles on Lenya, we’d like to talk about
            what Lenya is and what approach it takes in content management, including its
            advantages and disadvantages.</p>
        
        <section id="history">
                    <title>History</title>
        
        <p>Lenya was started by Michael Wechner in early 1999 as a way to document a journal on
            pattern formation. From there, he co-started a company called
            <a href="ext:wyona">Wyona</a> which continued to work on the project
            until the spring of 2003, where the project was donated to the Apache Software
            Foundation.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="approach"><title>Approach to Content Management</title>
        
        <p>Lenya’s approach to content management is just that: content management. While
            <a href="http://www.textpattern.com/">some</a> CMS’s allow users to
            change the styling of pages in the graphical interface of the application, Lenya
            does not. Some consider this to be a big negative for Lenya, and for a large
            institution with multiple designers and CSS developers, it can be. We’ve been
            finding, however, as just one user that maintains the look and feel of Hiram’s
            website, this isn’t that bad. Instead of working in a webpage to update our CSS, we
            just upload it to the server.</p>
        
        <p>Of course, this means that the structural markup for the overall page layout is not
            managed in Lenya either, well, at least not through the graphical user
            interface. Instead, your page layout is done in XSL files, and when the page is
            accessed through your web browser, the content and the XSL template merge and get
            transformed into a valid HTML or XHTML document.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="goodstuff"><title>The good stuff</title>
        
        <p>What grabbed our attention with Lenya was how it went about presenting your content
            for editing. When you log in to your website through Lenya, you can click on the
            navigation in the pages as if you were browsing your website right there. Find
            something wrong in the text of one page as you browse? Just go to Edit -> WYSIWYG
            Editor and you’re taken to a page where you can change the content. Save your
            changes, then publish the updated page. It’s incredibly easy.</p>
        
        <p>What’s also nice is that the foundation of Lenya is built on XML which, of course, is
            great news for web standards gurus who will only work with XHTML. By default,
            Lenya uses HTML 4.0, but a quick change in one file will switch all your pages to
            XHTML Strict. And since it relies on XML, there’s no backend database that
            manages this: it’s all flat XML files stored on the server. Don’t get this
            confused, however, with having the ability to connect to a database as you would
            with any
            <a href="http://www.php.net/">PHP</a>-type language, because Lenya can
            definitely do this as well.</p>
        
        <p>And as any good CMS would, information about the pages, like metadata, amongst
            other things, can be edited for each page and is kept separate from the content on
            the page itself. Lenya utilizes the
            <a href="http://www.dublincore.org/">Dublin Core</a> for its metadata
            tags in pages.</p>
            </section>
        
        <section id="downers"><title>Some downers</title>
        
        <p>OK, so there are some downers. The terminology takes a bit of getting used to. For
            example, “assets” are documents, images, or anything you want to link to in the
            page that isn’t text. Some things just don’t happen by default in Lenya: they
            require some extra programming. For example, say you add a new item in your site’s
            navigation, but it doesn’t have a page on your website, it just links to an outside
            site. There’s no nice way of doing this in the graphical interface. A login to the
            server to edit the publication’s sitemap will provide this functionality.</p>
        
        <p>Also, Lenya runs on top of
            <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/">Apache Cocoon</a>, which is not the
            downer, but the time required to learn it makes a lot of people give up quickly.
            
                <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/2.1/userdocs/concepts/index.html#Basic+Mechanisms.">
                Pipelines</a> are the big key to understanding how a page is created in
            Lenya, and trust me, that will take some getting used to when you want to do
            something that doesn’t fit the general site provided for you as an example. With
            that, it’s much harder to find a company that will host Lenya for you – chances are
            you’ll need to have a server of your own.</p>
        
        <p>One last thing for picky web developers: getting a website to have clean URLs is a
            bit tricky. Even we have yet to get this working exactly the way we would like it to.
            And with Lenya and clean URLs comes a much more detailed look into configurations
            with the Apache web server than you are probably used to, which does take some
            time.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="next"><title>What’s next?</title>
        
        <p>So, you read the advantages and disadvantages and you want to take the plunge into
            Lenya? Good, because in my next article we’ll be explaining the methods we took to
            get Lenya up and running on our RedHat Enterprise Linux server. Don’t worry, you
            won’t need this specific operating system to make Lenya work. Lenya can run on
            pretty much any UNIX/Linux server and (even) Microsoft Windows.</p>
            </section>
    </body>
</document>