<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2002-2004 The Apache Software Foundation
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>The Lenya Content Repository</title> 
  </header>
  <body>
    
    <note>This document is a draft. It does not reflect the current implementation, but will evolve alongside the code.</note>
    
    <section>
      <title>The Lenya Repository API</title>
      <p>
        The Lenya repository API comprises the following interfaces:
      </p>
      <dl>
        <dt><strong>Repository</strong></dt>
        <dd>The repository object is the entry point to the Lenya repository. It provides access to
        the document type registry and allows to create sessions.</dd>
        <dt><strong>Session</strong></dt>
        <dd>A session provides access to the publications and methods for transaction handling. Pending
        changes are not written to the repository until the session is saved.</dd>
        <dt><strong>Publication</strong></dt>
        <dd>A publication consists of an arbitrary set of areas.</dd>
        <dt><strong>Area</strong></dt>
        <dd>An area consists of a set of content nodes with a site structure associated to them.</dd>
        <dt><strong>Content</strong></dt>
        <dd>The content object provides access to the content nodes.</dd>
        <dt><strong>ContentNode</strong></dt>
        <dd>A content node holds several language versions of a content item. Each content node
          has an ID which is unique in its area. Each content node has a <em>document type</em>,
          which applies to all language versions of the node. When a content node is added, the
          document type must be specified. Only document types which are registered in the
          repository's document type registry are supported.</dd>
        <dt><strong>Document</strong></dt>
        <dd>A document is a language version of a content item. Each document has the following properties:
          <ul>
            <li>the language,</li>
            <li>the content length, and</li>
            <li>the last modification date.</li>
          </ul>
          The document provides access to its content via the methods <code>getInputStream()</code>
          and <code>getOutputStream()</code>.
        </dd>
        <dt><strong>DocumentType</strong></dt>
        <dd>The document type of a content node denotes the type of contents which may be stored
          in its documents. A document type is identified by a unique name. It may provide a
          schema, which can be used to validate XML contents upon saving. Furthermore, the mime type
          of documents is defined by the document type.</dd>
        <dt><strong>MetaData</strong></dt>
        <dd>...</dd>
        <dt><strong>Site</strong></dt>
        <dd>The site object provides access to the site structure.</dd>
        <dt><strong>SiteNode</strong></dt>
        <dd>The site structure is a tree consisting of site nodes. Each site node has an ID which
          is unique among its siblings. Thus, a site node can be located using a unique path
          of the form <code>/sections/news/message003</code>.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Repository Layout</title>
      
      <p>
        Lenya ships with a content repository implementation which is based on the
        <a href="http://www.jcp.org/aboutJava/communityprocess/final/jsr170/">Java Content Repository</a> API.
        The JCR repository used by Lenya comprises a set of workspaces, each of which represent an area
        of the document structure. For each area that is declared by a publication, a repository workspace
        is created.
      </p>
      <p>
        Publications are orthogonal to workspaces. Each publication can declare its own set of areas.
        Thus, the set of workspaces in the Lenya repository derives from the union of all areas declared by publications.
      </p>
      <figure src="site:repositoryWorkspaces.img" alt="Repository Workspaces"/>
      
      <p>
        The children of the root node of a workspace are called <em>publication JCR nodes</em>. Each publication JCR node
        has two children:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>the <em>content</em> JCR node, and</li>
        <li>the <em>site</em> JCR node.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        The content JCR node can have an arbitrary number of child nodes, which are called <em>content </em>
      </p>
      
      
    </section>
    
  </body>
</document>
