<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!-- $Id: index.xml 55543 2004-10-26 00:14:59Z gregor $ -->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document>
	<header>
		<title>Apache Lenya</title>
		<version/>
		<type/>
		<authors>
      <person name="Lenya community" email="dev@lenya.apache.org"/>
		</authors>
	</header>
	<body>
        <section id="apacheCon">
                <title>Come to ApacheCon US 2004</title>
                 <p>
          <link href="http://apachecon.com/2004/US/">
            <img src="http://apache.org/images/ac2004_170x100.gif"
              alt="apachecon 2004 logo" width="170" height="100" />
          </link>
          </p><p>
          <link href="http://apachecon.com/2004/US/">ApacheCon US 2004</link>
            (13-17 November 2004). ApacheCon is the conference for all
            things Apache. Come along and learn about a range of new
            technologies, meet some Apache folks and share the knowledge.
            See more information about
           <link href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/conferences.html">Apache Conferences</link>.
        </p>
        </section>
        <section id="introduction" >
                <title>Introduction</title>
                <p>
Apache Lenya is an Open-Source Content Management System written in Java and based on open standards such as 
XML and XSLT. Lenya is built on top of Apache Cocoon and other components from the Apache Software Stack. 
Its XML-centric architecture allows for content delivery targeted to the capabilities of various devices, 
and avoids data lock-in. Apache Lenya is built around Off the Shelf components from the Apache Software Foundation.</p>
<p>Apache Lenya comes with the features you can expect of a modern Content Management System, such as 
    Revision Control, Scheduling, a built-in Search Engine, seperate Staging Areas, and Workflow.</p><p>
Because Apache Lenya is based on Cocoon, you can use <link href="ext:cocoon.2.1.features">Cocoon features</link> 
such as robust Caching, multi-channel output, it's many connectivity options to quickly build 
customized solutions to meet your specific needs that are not already covered by Apache Lenya today.</p>
<p>
Download Apache Lenya <link href="ext:incubator.lenya">here</link>.
</p>
        </section>

        <section id="news">
      <title>News and events</title>
      <ul>
       
        <li>The Lenya project has evolved to become a "top-level" Apache
         project.
        </li>
        <li><strong>Incubating Apache Lenya 1.2 released</strong> (June 27, 2004) </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
		
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Features</strong>
			</title>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Authoring</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> Browser-based WYSIWYG Editors that validate input against a Relax
NG Schema. This prevents invalid markup as produced by other WYSIWYG
editors, and allows to enforce web site style guidelines. Lenya ships with the <link href="http://bxe.oscom.org">BXE</link> 
and <link href="http://kupu.oscom.org">Kupu</link> editors out of the box. Lenya asset management 
and link management are integrated into BXE.
</li>
<li> A forms editor is available for situations where a full-blown 
    WYSIWYG editor is overkill or where legacy browsers need to be supported.
</li>
<li>Pages that are being edited are automatically locked for other users, preventing conflicting changes 
    to the same page.
</li>
<li> Each edit of a page creates a new revision. It is possible to revert to any previous revision of a page.
</li>
		 </ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Workflow</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> Lenya contains a customizable workflow engine that uses an easy XML format to define workflows. 
    Standard one- and two-stage workflows ship with Lenya. Users can be notified by email about pending approvals.
</li>
<li> Workflow events such as publishing or deactivating a page can be scheduled.
</li>
<li>Lenya supports seperate authoring, staging and live areas. For convenience, the staging area is 
    disabled by default.
</li>
<li>All workflow steps are logged, providing an audit trail.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Internationalization</strong>
			</title>
<ul>
<li> Pages can be created in multiple languages with no impact on your site structure. Lenya automatically 
    displays your page in the default languge if it is not available in a specific language.
</li>
<li> The Lenya user interface is currently localized in spanish, italian, french, german and english.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Layout</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> The publications concept allows reuse of the information architecture of a site and brings modularity 
    to the content level. Different publications can share content and business logic, and new 
    publications can be created with a cloning process.
</li>
<li> Lenya supports XHTML+CSS templating, eliminating the need to learn yet another templating language. 
    Wherever possible, Lenya uses CSS for styling, therefore enforcing the seperation of content and layout.

</li>
<li>The navigation framework automatically creates navigation items such as menus, breadcrumb paths and tabs. 
    A sitemap can be easily created.
</li>
<li>Lenya has clean URLs and is thus optimally accessible for search engines.
</li>
<li>There are no restrictions on the nesting of templates. You can use 
    any template you have defined at any level of your site structure thanks to the URI parametrizer.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Site Management</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> Lenya allows you to move, copy, rename, archive or delete individual pages or whole parts 
    of your site within an easy to use site view that shows you the pages of your site in an explorer-like view.
</li>
<li> Each page has tabs for easy access to meta data, assets, workflow status, revisions, access control 
    and scheduling.

</li>
<li> The archive function allows you to deactiviate pages and store them in an archive.
</li>
<li> Deleted pages can be retrieved from the trash.
</li>
<li> Each page can have Dublin Core metadata assigned. Other metadata standards can easily be added if required.
</li>
<li> Asset management allows you to keep track of images and documents that belong to a page.
</li>
<li> Link management ensures that internal links are not shown if the target page doesn't exist or the 
    user has no access to it. Link management also warns users about broken links when they publish a page.
</li>
<li> Lenya checks if parent pages of a page to be published are already live to avoid inconsistent sites.

</li>
<li>Deployment is flexible: Sites can be served dynamically by the authoring server (for small deployments) 
    or another servlet container. It is also possible to export content statically or to use Apache as a proxy.
</li>
<li>If used with a reverse proxy, Lenya can be configured to rewrite URLs based on the site structure of 
    the live site.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Security</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> Each page or parts of your site can be protected by SSL. Protect just the parts of your site that need 
    protection for best performance.
</li>
<li> The Lenya access control allows you to restrict access to parts of your site to members of a group or 
    individuals. You can also restrict specific Lenya functionalities, such as editing, approval or 
    administrative features.
</li>

<li> Lenya users can be authenticated against an LDAP server.
</li>
<li> Access can also be controlled by IP ranges.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Misc</strong>
			</title>
<ul>
<li> A Windows Installer makes installation on windows a 3-click process.
</li>
<li> Apache Lucene is integrated into Lenya to offer full-text and field search.

</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Under the Hood</strong>
			</title>
<ul>
<li> The integration with Cocoon has been improved. For the next release, it is planned to move Lenya to a 
    block-based system which should make it much easier to mix and match Cocoon and Lenya components.
</li>
<li> Unit Tests help to discover regressions in the code.
</li>
<li> A publication API that defines a interface for common CMS operations.
</li>
<li> A fallback concept allows you to selectively override core functionality in your site where needed. 
    Default implementations are provided for convenience and ease of development.

</li>
<li> Lenya uses Ant for portable scripting. This allows you to integrate Lenya into your enviroment and 
    accomplish custom tasks easily.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
