<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!-- $Id: index.xml 55543 2004-10-26 00:14:59Z gregor $ -->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
	<header>
		<title>Apache Lenya - Open Source Content Management (Java/XML)</title>
	</header>
	<body>
<p><img src="images/menubar.png" alt="Screenshot of the Apache Lenya menu bar"/></p><p>
Apache Lenya is an Open Source Java/XML Content Management Syxstem and comes with revision control, site management, scheduling, search, WYSIWYG editors, and workflow.
Please see some <a href="screenshots.html">screenshots</a> or try the <a href="ext:lenya.demo">Demo</a>.</p>

   	<section id="news">
      <title>News</title>
      <ul>
        <li>Two Lenya presentations at <a href="ext:apachecon">ApacheCon Europe 2005</a> (Stuttgart, Germany
18-22 July 2005)</li>
        <li><a href="site:download14">Lenya 1.2.4 released</a> (June 25, 2005)</li>
        <li><a href="site:download14">Lenya 1.4alpha1 released</a> (June 12, 2005)</li>
        <li>New <a href="site:faq">Lenya How-To's</a> posted (May 15, 2005) </li>
        <li>New <a href="site:tutorial">Lenya tutorials</a> posted (April 24, 2005) </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    
    <section id="download">
    <title>Downloads</title>
    <p>Current stable version of Apache Lenya is 1.2.4. This is the recommended version for production. You will at least need the Java 2 Platform, Standard Edition, version 1.4.2. Please follow the <a href="site:install">installation instructions</a>.</p>
    <ul>
    	<li>Lenya 1.2.4 <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.exe">Windows binary</a> (Windows Installer) <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.exe.asc">ASC Signature</a> <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.exe.md5">MD5 Checksum</a></li>
    	<li>Lenya 1.2.4 <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.zip">Windows binary</a> (ZIP archive) <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.zip.asc">ASC Signature</a> <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.zip.md5">MD5 Checksum</a></li>
    	<li>Lenya 1.2.4 <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/SOURCES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-src.zip">Windows source code</a> (ZIP archive) <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/SOURCES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-src.zip.asc">ASC Signature</a> <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/SOURCES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-src.zip.md5">MD5 Checksum</a></li>
    	<li>Lenya 1.2.4 <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.tar.gz">Unix binary</a> (tar.gz archive) <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.tar.gz.asc">ASC Signature</a> <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/BINARIES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-bin.tar.gz.md5">MD5 Checksum</a></li>
    	<li>Lenya 1.2.4 <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/SOURCES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-src.tar.gz">Unix source code</a> (tar.gz archive) <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/SOURCES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-src.tar.gz.asc">ASC Signature</a> <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lenya/SOURCES/apache-lenya-1.2.4-src.tar.gz.md5">MD5 Checksum</a></li>
    </ul>
    <p>The Apache Software Foundation has <a href="http://people.apache.org/~henkp/cgi-bin/md5.cgi">more information on ASC Signatures and MD5 checksums</a>.</p>
    <p>Please go to the <a href="site:download12">download section</a> of version 1.2 for more download options such as SVN.</p>
    <p>You may want to <a href="site:download14">download</a> the current development version 1.4, which is still under heavy development and should not be used for production yet.</p>

    </section>
		
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Features</strong>
			</title>
<p>If you have additional requirements beyond the 
features listed below, you have access to all <a href="ext:cocoon.2.1.features">Apache Cocoon features</a> to develop them.</p>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Authoring</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> Browser-based WYSIWYG Editors that validate input against a Relax
NG Schema. This prevents invalid markup as produced by other WYSIWYG
editors, and allows to enforce web site style guidelines. ships with the <a href="http://bxe.oscom.org">BXE</a> 
and <a href="ext:kupu">Kupu</a> editors out of the box. Asset management 
and link management are integrated into BXE and Kupu.
</li>
<li> A forms editor is available for situations where a full-blown 
    WYSIWYG editor is overkill or where legacy browsers need to be supported.
</li>
<li>Pages that are being edited are automatically locked for other users, preventing conflicting changes 
    to the same page.
</li>
<li> Each edit of a page creates a new revision. It is possible to revert to any previous revision of a page.
</li>
		 </ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Workflow</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> A customizable workflow engine that uses an easy XML format to define workflows. 
    Standard one- and two-stage workflows are included. Users can be notified by email about pending approvals.
</li>
<li> Workflow events such as publishing or deactivating a page can be scheduled.
</li>
<li>Supports separate authoring, staging and live areas. For convenience, the staging area is 
    disabled by default.
</li>
<li>All workflow steps are logged, providing an audit trail.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Internationalization</strong>
			</title>
<ul>
<li> Pages can be created in multiple languages with no impact on your site structure. Lenya automatically 
    displays your page in the default languge if it is not available in a specific language.
</li>
<li> The user interface is currently localized in spanish, italian, french, german, english, dutch and japanese.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Layout</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> The publications concept allows reuse of the information architecture of a site and brings modularity 
    to the content level. Different publications can share content and business logic, and new 
    publications can be created with a cloning process.
</li>
<li>Supports XHTML+CSS templating, eliminating the need to learn yet another templating language. 
    Wherever possible, uses CSS for styling, therefore enforcing the separation of content and layout.

</li>
<li>The navigation framework automatically creates navigation items such as menus, breadcrumb paths and tabs. 
    A sitemap can be easily created.
</li>
<li>Produces clean URLs without request parameters and is thus optimally accessible for search engines.
</li>
<li>There are no restrictions on the nesting of templates. You can use 
    any template you have defined at any level of your site structure thanks to the URI parametrizer.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Site Management</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li>Allows you to move, copy, rename, archive or delete individual pages or whole parts 
    of your site within an easy to use site view that shows you the pages of your site in an explorer-like view.
</li>
<li> Each page has tabs for easy access to meta data, assets, workflow status, revisions, access control 
    and scheduling.

</li>
<li> The archive function allows you to deactiviate pages and store them in an archive.
</li>
<li> Deleted pages can be retrieved from the trash.
</li>
<li> Each page can have Dublin Core metadata assigned. Other metadata standards can easily be added if required.
</li>
<li> Asset management allows you to keep track of images and documents that belong to a page.
</li>
<li> Link management ensures that internal links are not shown if the target page doesn't exist or the 
    user has no access to it. Link management also warns users about broken links when they publish a page.
</li>
<li>Checks if parent pages of a page to be published are already live to avoid inconsistent sites.

</li>
<li>Deployment is flexible: Sites can be served dynamically by the authoring server (for small deployments) 
    or another servlet container. It is also possible to export content statically or to use Apache as a proxy.
</li>
<li>If used with a reverse proxy, can be configured to rewrite URLs based on the site structure of 
    the live site.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Security</strong>
			</title>
			<ul>
<li> Each page or parts of your site can be protected by SSL. Protect just the parts of your site that need 
    protection for best performance.
</li>
<li> The access control allows you to restrict access to parts of your site to members of a group or 
    individuals. You can also restrict specific functionalities, such as editing, approval or 
    administrative features.
</li>

<li>Users can be authenticated against an LDAP server.
</li>
<li> Access can also be controlled by IP ranges.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Misc</strong>
			</title>
<ul>
<li> A Windows Installer makes installation on windows a 3-click process.
</li>
<li> Apache Lucene is integrated for full-text and field search.

</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				<strong>Under the Hood</strong>
			</title>
<ul>
<li>Based on Apache Cocoon. All Cocoon components can be used to develop customized functionality.
</li>
<li> Unit Tests help to discover regressions in the code.
</li>
<li> A publication API that defines a interface for common CMS operations.
</li>
<li> A fallback concept allows you to selectively override core functionality in your site where needed. 
    Default implementations are provided for convenience and ease of development.

</li>
<li>Uses Ant for portable scripting.
</li>
</ul>
		</section>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
