<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
xmlns:lenya="http://apache.org/cocoon/lenya/page-envelope/1.0" 
xhtml:dummy="FIXME:keepNamespace" dc:dummy="FIXME:keepNamespace" 
lenya:dummy="FIXME:keepNamespace">
    <!-- the root element indicates the doctype -->
    <lenya:meta>
        <dc:title>DC Title</dc:title>
        <dc:creator>Christian Egli</dc:creator>
        <dc:subject>DC Subject</dc:subject>
        <dc:description>Abstract that can be used on an overview page</dc:description>
        <dc:publisher/>
        <dc:contributor/>
        <dc:date>2003-5-21</dc:date>
        <dc:type/>
        <dc:format/>
        <dc:identifier/>
        <dc:source/>
        <dc:language>en</dc:language>
        <dc:relation/>
        <dc:coverage/>
        <dc:rights>DC Rights</dc:rights>
    </lenya:meta>
  <head>
    <title>Concepts</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <h1>Concepts</h1>
    
    <h2>Publications</h2>
    
    <p>In Apache Lenya, a website is called a
    <strong>publication</strong>.</p>
    
    <h2>Areas: Authoring and Live</h2>

    <p>Apache Lenya separates between different areas:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>The authoring area is for creating and editing of
      content. All CMS functions are available here.</li>

      <li>Once the content has been published it is moved to the live
      area. The live area can be served by a web server directly or
      you can add another intermediate step where the content is
      replicated from the live area to the actual web server. In any
      case the live area simply serves as a preview to the content
      that will be served by the web server.</li>
    </ul>
    
    <h2>Document types</h2>

    <p>As Apache Lenya is based on Apache Cocoon, it has strong XML and
    XSLT foundations. It is possible to ensure that a document
    conforms to an XML schema. Typically you define different types of
    documents, like an news article or an opinion piece, conforming to
    different XML schemas. These different types are referred to as
    document types. They are used to ensure the XML schema conformance
    when editing and typically also when preparing a presentation of
    the document, where an opinion piece has a different layout than a
    news article.</p>

  </body>
</html>
