<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Wyona Concepts</title>
    <version/> 
    <type/> 
    <authors>
      <person name="" email=""/> 
      <person name="Marc von Wattenwyl" email="marc.vonwattenwyl@wyona.org"/>
    </authors> 
  </header> 
  <body>


    <section><title>Roles of the Wyona Users</title> 

<p>
  All users of the Wyona-CMS have roles assigned to their usernames. These roles 
  are the basis of the authorization scheme used throughout the application. The roles
  and their respective authorizations are totally customizable through an
  administration panel.
</p>
<p>
  All roles belong to one of these main groups:</p>
<ol>
  <li><jump href="bas-roles.html#roles_admin">Administrators</jump></li>
  <li><jump href="bas-roles.html#roles_author">Authors</jump></li>
  <li><jump href="bas-roles.html#roles_designer">Designers</jump></li>
  <li><jump href="bas-roles.html#roles_publisher">Publishers</jump></li>
</ol>

<anchor id="roles_admin"/>
<section><title>Administrators</title>
<p>
  Administrators are responsible for:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Maintaining users and their profiles (e.g. assigned roles)</li>
    <li>Maintaining the site/publication description</li>
    <li>Maintaining page descriptions</li>
    <li>Configuring the Wyona-CMS:</li>
    <ul>
      <li>Assigning editors to edit tasks</li>
      <li>...</li>
    </ul>
  </ul>
<p>
  For most/all of these tasks, specific configuration pages are provided
  whithin the Wyona-CMS's <em>Administration Block</em> to shield the 
  administrator from the internals of xml/xsl technologies and the
  Cocoon environment.
</p>
</section>

<anchor id="roles_author"/>
<section><title>Authors</title>
<p>
  Authors are the users responsible for content creation and management, they use
  the specific editors to maintain the content in a controlled and consistant way.
  Typically, authors are never confronted with design choices and/or xml/xsl documents, 
  they only work whithin the Wyona-CMS environment, i.e. a www-browser. The content
  is first placed in a staging context, waiting for a <link href="#roles_publisher">
  publisher</link> to publish it so that it can be viewed by external viewers of
  the publication.
</p>
</section>
<anchor id="roles_designer"/>
<section><title>Designers</title>
<p>
  Designers are users responsible for maintaining the layout and style of the
  publication. Typically, they work directly with the xsl and css files
  used to transform the publication for presentation (e.g. in a browser), as
  well as the required graphic files. All these files are located in a separate
  branch of the application tree for convenience (see also 
  <link href="#directories">Directory structure</link> below). To simplify the 
  designer's work, a <em>"publication explorer"</em> could be provided, that helps
  to navigate the publishing tree (by reading sitedef.xml) and to identify the content
  files and their structure (by reading the page descriptor files), and that 
  can be linked to any xml/xsl-editor.
</p>
</section>

<anchor id="roles_publisher"/>
<section><title>Publishers</title>
<p>
  Publishers are users that have permission to add staged content to the live
  publication. This role group is primarily introduced for workflow management
  purposes. In practice, publisher roles will be combined with author roles to 
  model the workflow of the content management environment, allowing for reviewing
  and editing activities.
</p>

</section>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>