<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Creating/Importing Content (Resource)</title>
    <version/>
    <type/>
    <authors>
      <person name="Michael Wechner" email="michael.wechner@wyona.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section><title>Introduction</title>
<p>
There are many different ways to create respectively import content into 
a Content Management System. You can upload an image, you can create a document
based on some form input or you can create a document by copying a sample document.
The following use cases shall illustrate some possible situations in more detail.
The goal is to develop a generic API for resource creation.
</p>
    </section>
    <section><title>Use Cases</title>
      <section><title>Create Article (New Wyona Times)</title>
        <ol>
          <li>Go to the section page (e.g. International Section)</li>
          <li>Click in the File Menu on "New Article"</li>
          <li>Confirm by clicking ok on the "Create new article" screen</li>
          <li>Sample article with all required elements will be copied onto 
a new article, where identifier has been created automatically based on the current date</li>
          <li>Author/Editor will be redirected to newly created Article</li>
          <li>The system inserts in the background the newly created article at 
the top of the refered section page</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section><title>Create Article (unipublic)</title>
        <ol>
          <li>Go to the section page (e.g. Gesundheit)</li>
          <li>Click in the File Menu on "New Article"</li>
          <li>On the "Create new article" screen enter an identifier (based on Filemaker ID)</li>
          <li>Sample article with all required elements will be copied onto a new article with the identifier entered by the editor</li>
          <li>The system inserts the newly created article at the top of the refered section page</li>
          <li>Author/Editor will be redirected back to the refered section page</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section><title>Upload Image (unipublic)</title>
        <ol>
          <li>Go to the article page</li>
          <li>Click on a "new image" icon for instance between two paragraphs</li>
          <li>On the "Upload new image" screen click on "browse" in order to select an
image from your local harddisk. Enter a filename as name for the image on the server. Click "upload image".</li>
          <li>The system stores the image "beside" the refered article and creates a meta file (XML) for the
image with fields such as "Creation Date", User", "Filename", "Mime-Type", etc.</li>
          <li>The system inserts an XInclude into the article (for instance between two paragraphs) referencing the meta file</li>
          <li>The user will be redirected to the refered article</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section><title>Submit Story (Wyona News and Comments)</title>
        <ol>
          <li>Click on "Submit Story" in the main navigation on the left hand side. You
will be redirected to a form.</li>
          <li>Complete the form (e.g. title, lead, text, category, etc.).</li>
          <li>Submit the form and you will be redirected to a preview</li>
          <li>Confirm the Preview or edit the form once again.</li>
          <li>After confirming the preview, the User/Author will be redirected to a "Thank you" screen.</li>
          <li>The systems adds the new story to the list of submitted stories (submissions list) and
notifies the appropriate editors via email.</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section><title>Related Information</title>
        <p>
	<fork href="http://jakarta.apache.org/slide/javadoc/org/apache/slide/content/ContentImpl.html">ContentImpl: Implementation of the Slide content interface</fork><br/>
	<fork href="http://dev.zope.org/Wikis/DevSite/Projects/ComponentArchitecture/CreateEmptyFile">Zope: CreateEmptyFile</fork><br/>
	<fork href="http://dev.zope.org/Wikis/DevSite/Projects/ComponentArchitecture/CreateFileFromFormInput">Zope: CreateFileFromFormInput</fork><br/>
	</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>