<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>User's Guide -&gt; Authoring -&gt; Editing Content</title>
    <version/>
    <type/>
    <authors>
      <person name="" email=""/>
      <person name="" email=""/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section><title>Wyona's HTML Editor</title>
        <p>
	  This is a simple editor using standard HTML forms, thus designed for 
	  maximum compatibility. It should work with almost any browser that is in use 
	  today, and provides a solid fallback positions, if the fancier editors are
	  not available. It provides full authoring, staging and publishing
	  functionality. The only thing it lacks is WYSIWYG capabilities, but this
	  should not really pose a problem because one can always check the 
	  potential live appearance of the document being edited with the click
	  of a button.
	</p>

	<p>
	  The use of the editor is very simple, thus the documentation provided
	  here is also minimal. If you have questions which are not answered here,
	  please use the <fork href="http://www.lenya.org/mailing-lists.html">mailing list</fork>.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Just a few points to keep in mind:
	</p>

 	<ul>
  	  <li>
       	        The entry fields are generally capable of accepting XHTML markup,
      		so you have some possibilities for enhancing the default display
      		behaviour. Especially practical is the possibility to include links, 
      		but even tables are possible! Just remember to stay XHTML
      		compatible, some things that are legal in HTML are not allowed
     		in XHTML. If in doubt, check the <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/WD-xhtml1-20011004/">
      		W3C Working Draft</link>.
  	  </li>
  	  <li>
      		The buttons/graphics displayed are depending on what the editing
      		possibilities are at the moment, as defined in the document descriptor.
      		So don't panic when some widgets disappear, probably you just don't
      		need them.
  	  </li>
	  </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>