<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Meta Data</title>
    <version/>
    <type/>
    <authors>
      <person name="Christian Egli" email="egli@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>Meta data is kept directly inside the xml document. It is
      based on the <link href="http://dublincore.org">Dublin Core</link>
      standard.</p>

      <p>There are basically three use cases:</p>
      <ol>
	<li>Create Meta Data</li>
	<li>Display Meta Data</li>
	<li>Modify Meta Data</li>
      </ol>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Implementation</title> 

      <p></p>

      <section>
	<title>Create Meta Data</title>

	<p>Upon creation of a document a sample is copied from the
	sample doctype directory. This sample already contains some
	sample meta data. The creator then applies an XSLT
	transformation to this sample which adapts the sample values
	to the values suplied in the creator request. This values are
	partially filled in by the user (subject, desciption, etc.)
	and partly by the system (creator, creation data). This is
	done in the <code>create</code> ant task which at the end
	invokes an xslt task which applies the
	<code>addMetaData.xsl</code> stylesheet which adapts the meta
	data according to the request values.</p>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Display Meta Data</title>

	<p>The display of meta data is handled by the <code>meta.xsp</code> xsp.</p>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Modify Meta data</title>

	<p>The modification of meta data is handled in the
	<code>info.xmap</code> sitemap. The matcher makes sure to
	check the document out before the modification and checking it
	back in after the modification. This is done using the
	<code>ReservedCheckoutTestAction</code> and
	<code>ReservedCheckinAction</code>.  If there is an error the
	request is redirected to the meta data screen which displays a
	warning saying that the checkout or checkin failed and who was
	locking the document since what date and time.</p>

	<p>Once the document is checked out the madifications are
	applied with the help of an ant task. There is a target named
	<code>save-meta-data</code> which simply invokes the ant task
	<code>WriteDCParametersTask</code>.  This task saves the meta
	data using the <code>DublinCore</code> interface.</p>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Involved classes, XSPs and XSLTs</title>

      <p>The following classes, XSPs and XSLTs are involved in meta
      data handling:</p>
      <dl>
	<dt>org.apache.lenya.cms.ant.WriteDCParametersTask</dt>
	<dd>A simple ant task which saves the meta data which is
	  passed as arguments to file using the
	<code>DublinCore</code> class.</dd>
	<dt>$publication-id/config/tasks/targets.xml</dt>
	<dd>Defines the <code>save-meta-data</code> target which
	handles saving of meta data with the help of the
	<code>WriteDCParametersTask</code> ant task. Also defines
	the <code>create</code> target which is used create new
	documents and to change the meta data according to the request
	values from the creation request.</dd>
	<dt>org.apache.lenya.cms.publication.DublinCore</dt>
	<dd>A simple interface to save and retrieve dublin core meta
	data.</dd>
	<dt>org.apache.lenya.cms.cocoon.acting.ReservedCheckoutTestAction</dt>
	<dd>Action that tests if a document can be checked out and if
	yes does check it out (See <link
	href="../revisioncontrol/revisioncontroller.html">Revision Controller</link>).</dd>
	<dt>org.apache.lenya.cms.cocoon.acting.ReservedCheckinAction</dt>
	<dd>Action that checks a document in (See <link
	href="../revisioncontrol/revisioncontroller.html">Revision Controller</link>).</dd>
	<dt>src/webapp/lenya/content/info/meta.xsp, src/webapp/lenya/xslt/info/info.xsl</dt>
	<dd>Handle the display of the meta data in the info area. This
	is also a form which can be used to modify the meta data via a
	POST request.</dd>
	<dt>src/webapp/lenya/xslt/authoring/addMetaData.xsl</dt>
	<dd>Simple XSLT stylesheet that modifies the meta data
	according to the input parameters.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
