<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Related Projects</title>
    <version/>
    <type/>
    <authors>
      <person name="Michael Wechner" email="michael.wechner@wyona.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
<p>
This list is featuring projects which are closely related to Apache Lenya.
</p>

<p>
Open Source Content Management Systems/Frameworks overviews can be found at
<link href="http://www.oscom.org">oscom.org</link> or
<link href="http://www.cmsinfo.org">cmsinfo.org</link>.
</p>

<p>
More information on Cocoon-based projects can be found at
<link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/2.0/link/projects.html">http://cocoon.apache.org/2.0/link/projects.html</link>.
</p>

<section><title>CocoBlog</title>
<p>
CocoBlog is a free <link href="http://newhome.weblogs.com/historyOfWeblogs">weblogging</link> software tool based on Apache Cocoon and Apache XIndice
<link href="http://www.beblogging.com/blog/docs">http://www.beblogging.com/blog/docs</link>.
</p>
</section>

<section><title>Cocoon</title>
<p>
Apache Cocoon is an XML publishing framework that raises the usage of XML and XSLT
technologies for server applications to a new level. Designed for performance and
scalability around pipelined SAX processing, Cocoon offers a flexible environment
based on a separation of concerns between content, logic, and style. To top this all
off, Cocoons centralized configuration system and sophisticated caching help you to
create, deploy, and maintain rock-solid XML server applications.
</p>
<p>
<link href="http://cocoon.apache.org">http://cocoon.apache.org</link>
</p>
</section>


<section><title>Maverick</title>
<p>
Maverick is a Model-View-Controller (aka "Model 2") framework for web publishing
using Java and J2EE. It is a minimalist framework which focuses solely on MVC logic,
allowing you to generate presentation using a variety of templating and transformation
technologies.
</p>
<p>
<link href="http://mav.sourceforge.net">http://mav.sourceforge.net</link>
</p>
</section>


<section><title>Slide</title>
<p>
The Slide project main module is a Content Management and Integration System, which
can be seen as a low-level content management framework. Conceptually, it provides
a hierarchical organization of binary content which can be stored into arbitrary,
heterogenous, distributed data stores. In addition, Slide integrates security, locking,
versioning, as well as many other services.
</p>
<p>
<link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/slide/">http://jakarta.apache.org/slide/</link>
</p>
</section>


</body>
</document>
