<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Asset Management</title>
    <version/>
    <type/>
    <authors>
      <person name="Christian Egli" email="egli@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Asset management is the process by which assets, such as pdf
      files or images are uploaded to the server and inserted into a
      document.</p>

      <p>Assets can be either inserted directly into a document or can
      be uploaded for later insertion. Direct insertion happens when
      editing the document, upload can be done in asset tab the site
      area.</p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Asset upload</title>
      <p>The upload of assets is done quite simply with an multipart
      request. The Upload screen is generated by an xsp
      (<code></code>) which handles asset upload, image upload, asset
      insertion and image insertion. This screen then generates the
      multipart request which is eventually handled by the
      <code>AssetUploadAction</code>. This action stores the asset in
      the resources directory and generates a meta file with the
      dublin core meta data that was passed in as request parameter or
      with data that was extracted from the request (mime type,
      size). Where the asset is stored is determined by the
      <code>ResourcesManager</code>.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>users</li>
        <li>machines</li>
        <li>the world (this idenitifiable is assigned to every client that tries to
          access the system)</li>
      </ul>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Identity</title>
      <p>An Identity is the collection of all Identifiables that have access to the
        system in the current session. The identity always contains the world and
        the machine that produced the request. If you logged in, the user is also
        contained in the identity.</p>
      <p>For instance, if you log in from the machine 192.168.0.16 as the user john,
        your identity contains this machine, this user and the world.</p>
    </section>


  </body>
</document>
