<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!-- $Id: index.xml 55543 2004-10-26 00:14:59Z gregor $ -->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Apache Lenya 2.0 Documentation</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <warning>
      Apache Lenya 2.0 is still under development and should not be used for production
    yet. A code freeze has been announced, and the release should be
      imminent.
    </warning>
    <note label="Help wanted!"> Since 2.0 is new and provides many 
      enhancements and new features, please help to document them with us. 
      Send documentation patches and use the Wiki. Thanks in advance :)</note>
    <p>
      More documentation (work in progress) can be found at the <a href="site:wiki/lenya/">Apache Lenya
    Wiki</a>. Please treat the Wiki with care for now, as much of the
      information there is outdated.
    </p>
    
    <section>
      <title>What's New in Lenya 2.0</title>
      <dl>
        <dt><a href="site:modules">Modularization</a></dt>
        <dd>
          The monolithic architecture has been replaced by a small generic core and
          various modules for specific purposes. This makes the codebase easier to understand
          and simplifies making custom functionality available in multiple publications.
        </dd>
        <dt><a href="site:repository">Improved Repository Access</a></dt>
        <dd>
          The refactored and extended repository API and new protocols make it easier
          to access and manipulate documents.
        </dd>
        <dt><a href="site:link-management">UUIDs for Internal Links</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Documents are now identified and referenced using
          <acronym title="Universally Unique Identifier">UUID</acronym>s.
          Static link rewriting is not necessary anymore.
        </dd>
        <dt><a href="site:resource_module_overview">Assets Are Treated as Documents</a></dt>
        <dd>
          There is no distinction between XML and binary documents anymore.
          Images, PDFs and other non-XML documents are now managed using the <em>resource</em>
          resource type. This simplifies both API and user interface.
        </dd>
        <dt><a href="site:ac-restricted">Improved Access Control</a></dt>
        <dd>
          It is now possible to explicitly deny permissions on specific pages.
        </dd>
        <dt><a href="site:metadata">Configurable Meta Data</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Additionally to the default <a href="http://dublincore.org">Dublin Core</a> meta data,
          you can now declare your own custom meta data element sets. For each meta data element,
          you can specify if it can be edited using the GUI or if it is used for internal purposes only.
        </dd>
        <dt><a href="site:publication-templating">Publication Templating</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Publication templating allows to re-use common functionality in multiple publications.
          All resources, like layout images, CSS, XSLT and Cocoon sitemap files, are inherited to
          child publications unless you explicitely override them.
        </dd>
        <dt><a href="site:usecase-framework-overview">Usecase Framework</a></dt>
        <dd>
          The usecase framework simplifies the implementation of user interaction functionality.
          It is not necessary to implement Cocoon sitemaps for each usecase anymore.
        </dd>
        <dt><a href="site:notification_module_overview">Simplified Notification, Inboxes</a></dt>
        <dd>
          It is now easier to trigger notification messages. Each user has a personal
          inbox to read and send messages.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    
  </body>
</document>
