<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Link Management</title>
    <version/>
    <type/>
    <authors>
      <person name="Christian Egli" email="egli@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>Link Managements deals with internal links, i.e. documents
      that refer to other documents within the same publication. These
      links might have to be changed</p>
      <ol>
	<li>if a document not yet live,</li>
	<li>if it is withdrawn from live or </li>
	<li>if its document-id has changed because it is moved to a
        different location within the site tree.</li>
	<li>references in authoring have to link to documents in
	<code>authoring</code>, however once they are published they
	need to refer to documents in <code>live</code></li>
      </ol>

      <p>These four cases have to be dealt with seperately.</p>
      <section>
	<title>A document is not yet live</title>
	<p>This case can happen if the user tries to publish a
	document which has a reference to another document which has
	not been published yet. The reference will be stale as the
	refered document is not in the live area yet. A warning will
	be issued during the publishing process.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>A document is withdrawn from live</title>
	<p>If a document which is has references to it is withdrawn
	from the live area the references will be stale, as the
	refered document is no longer available in the live area. A
	warning will be issued during the deactivation process.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>A document-id changes</title>
	<p>If a document is moved within the site tree such that it
	changes its document-id (e.g. cut a document and paste it
	somewhere else in the hierarchy in the site area) then all
	references to this document have to be changed. This is done
	transparently in the course of the paste.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Rewrite internal links in live</title>
	<p>Internal links refer to documents in authoring as long as
	they are not published. However as soon as they are published,
	i.e. reside in the live area their references have to go to
	documents in the live area. A transformer takes care of
	rewriting the internal links.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Implementation</title> <p>The implementation is pretty
      straight-forward and is mostly handled in XSPs and associated
      helper classes. The heavy lifting us done is the class
      <code>Grep</code> and the helper class
      <code>DocumentReferencesHelper</code>. The <code>Grep</code>
      class can traverse the repository and find references to the
      current document or can also find references from the current
      document to other documents. A transformer
      (SimpleLinkRewritingTransformer) is used to rewrite the internal
      links in the live area.</p>

      <section>
	<title>A document is not yet live</title>

	<p>This is implemented as an extension to the publish xsp. It
	  queries the <code>DocumentReferencesHelper</code> (using the
	  <code>getInternalReferences</code> method) to ask if there
	  are references from the current document to other documents
	  which have not been published yet. The
	  <code>DocumentReferencesHelper</code> in turn uses the
	  <code>Grep#findPattern</code> method to search the current
	  document for patterns of a reference. The pattern is defined
	  in <code>DocumentReferencesHelper#getInternalLinkPattern</code>.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>A document is withdrawn from live</title>

	<p>This is implemented as an extension to the deactivate
	  xsp. It queries the <code>DocumentReferencesHelper</code>
	  (using the <code>getReferences</code> method) to ask if any
	  other documents refer to the current document. The
	  <code>DocumentReferencesHelper</code> in turn uses the
	  <code>Grep#find</code> method to search the repository for
	  documents which contain a patterns of a reference. The
	  pattern is defined in
	  <code>DocumentReferencesHelper#getReferencesSearchString()</code>.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>A document-id changes</title>

	<p>This is implemented with an ant task
	  (<code>org.apache.lenya.cms.ant.LinkRewriteTask</code>)
	  which traverses the repository and pipes all documents
	  through an XSLT stylesheet
	  (<code>unizh/pubs/unizh/xslt/linkRewrite.xsl</code>) to
	  modify all references to the document that changed its
	  document-id.
	</p>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Rewrite internal links in live</title>

	<p>The
	  <code>org.apache.lenya.cms.cocoon.transformation.SimpleLinkRewritingTransformer</code>
	  transformer takes care of rewriting internal links to ensure
	  they refer to the appropriate area.
	</p>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Involved classes, XSPs and XSLTs</title>

      <p>The following classes, XSPs and XSLTs are involved in link
      management:</p>
      <dl>
	<dt>org.apache.lenya.cms.publication.xsp.DocumentReferencesHelper</dt>
	<dd>A helper class for the publish and deactivate
	xsps. Defines the regular expressions for internal links. Has
	methods to deteremine all references from the current document
	to other documents (<code>getInternalReferences</code>) and to
	determine all references from other documents to the current
	document (<code>getReferences</code>).</dd>
	<dt>org.apache.lenya.search.Grep</dt>
	<dd>User by <code>DocumentReferencesHelper</code> to search
	for patterns in a file or in a directory tree.</dd> 
	<dt>org.apache.lenya.cms.ant.LinkRewriteTask</dt>
	<dd>An ant task that upon change of a document-id pipes all
	documents of the repository through a XSLT stylesheet which
	rewrites internal links that were refering to the old
	document-id to refere to the new one.</dd> 
	<dt>org.apache.lenya.cms.cocoon.transformation.SimpleLinkRewritingTransformer</dt>
	<dd>A transformer that rewrites internal links for the
	appropriate area.</dd>
	<dt>$publication-id/config/tasks/targets.xml</dt>
	<dd>Defines the <code>move-and-rewrite</code> the link
	rewriting in the case of a paste, i.e. when a document-id has changed.</dd> 
	<dt>unizh/pubs/unizh/xslt/linkRewrite.xsl</dt>
	<dd>The XSLT transformation used by
	<code>LinkRewriteTask</code> to actually rewrite the internal links.</dd>
	<dt>src/webapp/lenya/content/publishing/screen.xsp, src/webapp/lenya/xslt/publishing/publish-screen.xsl</dt>
	<dd>Query the <code>DocumentReferencesHelper</code> to display
	a warning in case the current document contains references to
	documents which have not been published yet.</dd>
	<dt>src/webapp/lenya/content/info/deactivate.xsp, src/webapp/lenya/xslt/info/deactivate.xsl</dt>
	<dd>Query the <code>DocumentReferencesHelper</code> to display
	a warning in case there are links to the current document
	which is about to be deactivated.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
