<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rss PUBLIC "-//Netscape Communications//DTD RSS 0.91//EN" "http://my.netscape.com/publish/formats/rss-0.91.dtd">
<rss version="0.91">
   <channel>
      <title>CMSWatch Trends and Features</title>
      <link>http://www.cmswatch.com</link>
      <description>Independent analyis, trends, and evaluations of Web Content Management products and practices</description>
      <language>en-us</language>
      <webMaster>webmaster@cmswatch.com</webMaster>
      <managingEditor>editor@cmswatch.com (Tony Byrne)</managingEditor>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2001 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2003 01:00:01 -0500</lastBuildDate>
      <image>
         <title>CMSWatch</title>
         <url>http://www.cmswatch.com/RSS/cmswatch_logo.gif</url>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com</link>
         <width>82</width>
         <height>36</height>
         <description>CMSWatch logo</description>
      </image>
      <item>
         <title>Tidying Up Your Site</title>
         <description>You may have heard about several new content migration tools hitting the marketplace, driven in part by the growing adoption of XML-based content management packages.  We'd just li...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?172</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Battle for the Windows-based CMS Mid-Market, Continued...</title>
         <description>RedDot and Microsoft frequently go head-to-head in competitions for Windows-based web CMS packages in the mid-market price/feature range.  Microsoft has not -- as many analysts pre...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?171</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>XML Editor Meets Hosted Document Management</title>
         <description>What happens when you combine a novel, browser-based XML editor with a hosted document repository?  Well, we're not really sure, but it will be interesting to find out.  A start-up...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?170</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Atomz gets WYSIWYG for Macs</title>
         <description>One shortcoming of CMS products in general (and hosted solutions in particular) is that they often provide WYSIWYG browser-based editing for only one platform.  Atomz just became o...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?169</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>divine Streamlines</title>
         <description>divine is slowly helping the world make better sense of the company's horizon-stretching product line.  Most recently, divine announced a reorganization into 3 product groups.  Thi...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?168</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Day-UK Starts the New Year on the Wrong Foot</title>
         <description>"Lets [sic] start the new year on the right foot," begins an e-mail message from Day's UK channel manager.  The three-sentence invitation to a partner meeting at an unnamed locatio...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?167</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Stellent Gets Serious in Europe</title>
         <description>We think the creation of formal user groups is a critical threshold for CMS vendors.  So it is worth noting that -- at a time when many US-based players are retrenching in Europe -...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?166</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>The Ideal CMS -- 2002</title>
         <description>What if you could graft the best features and attributes of individual Web content management packages into one single, ideal offering?  CMSWatch founder Tony Byrne takes a look at the vendor landscape circa 2002 and tries to assemble a "CMS Supergroup."  Warning: it's a large ensemble......</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/ProductWatch/FeaturedProduct?feature_id=83</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Updated CMSWatch Syndication Feed</title>
         <description>After several requests, we have added "TrendWatch" blurbs (you are reading one now) to our RSS syndication feed and update the file nightly.  You are welcome to retrieve.  BTW, CMS...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?165</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Enterprise Content Management at HBO</title>
         <description>HBO's Carl Hixson says of ECM, "there's no shrink-wrapped solution out there"......</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/PeopleWatch/FeaturedPeople?feature_id=82</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>All I Want for Christmas is My Two Front Ends</title>
         <description>For mixed PC/Mac authoring and editing environments, CMS tools still present a dilemma.  If you want to dispense with hand-coded HTML tagging in a browser, there are a wide variety...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?164</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Midgard in Action</title>
         <description>Can open-source CMS packages scale?  If the newly recast theater portal, Playbill.com, is any indication, the answer is, "Yes, with effort." The new version of Playbill is powered ...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?163</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Try Before You Buy</title>
         <description>CMS packages are complicated.  It's difficult to select the right one through proposals and demos alone.  Given the choice, most buyers would like to try out a commercial package b...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?162</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>XML Web Publishing</title>
         <description>John Callahan surveys the Apache "Cocoon" framework and suggests that some very nice Web creatures could take wing......</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/ProductWatch/FeaturedProduct?feature_id=81</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Microsoft Gets Textual with Office 11</title>
         <description>Well, there's a lot to say about the new XML support in Office 11 (now an early beta) and the implications for CMS. With the exception of the nifty (and badly needed!) XSLT generat...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?161</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>XMM: You Heard It Hear First</title>
         <description>You already know about "CMM," the doughty Capability Maturity Model for Software from Carnegie Mellon that helps you measure, evaluate, and improve your software processes.  Now al...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?160</link>
      </item>
     <textinput>
         <title>Search</title>
         <description>Search all of CMSWatch</description>
         <name>q</name>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/SiteSearch</link>
      </textinput>
   </channel>
</rss>