<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- edited with XML Spy v3.5 NT (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Tony Byrne (IDEV) -->
<!DOCTYPE rss PUBLIC "-//Netscape Communications//DTD RSS 0.91//EN" "http://my.netscape.com/publish/formats/rss-0.91.dtd">
<rss version="0.91">
   <channel>
      <title>Trends and Features from CMSWatch</title>
      <link>http://www.cmswatch.com</link>
      <description>Independent analyis, trends, and evaluations of Web Content Management products and practices</description>
      <language>en-us</language>
      <webMaster>webmaster@cmswatch.com</webMaster>
      <managingEditor>editor@cmswatch.com (Tony Byrne)</managingEditor>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2001 09:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <lastBuildDate>Sun 24 Mar 2002 09:05:02 -0800</lastBuildDate>
      <image>
         <title>CMSWatch</title>
         <url>http://www.cmswatch.com/RSS/cmswatch_logo.gif</url>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com</link>
         <width>82</width>
         <height>36</height>
         <description>CMSWatch logo</description>
      </image>
      <item>
         <title>Everyone talks about workflow, but what is it, really?</title>
         <description>This is the first in a series of articles excerpted from the forthcoming book, Content Management Bible by Bob Boiko, to be published by Hungry Minds later this year</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/TopicWatch/FeaturedTopic/?feature_id=47</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Can You Answer These Six Key Security Questions?</title>
         <description>Let’s fire away at a series of questions that might just get your CMS sales manager blustering. </description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/TopicWatch/FeaturedTopic/?feature_id=47</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>2nd Edition of CMS Report</title>
         <description>This week we announce the updated, Spring 2002 edition of The CMS Report. The report updates the product surveys from last year, and adds several new vendors to the mix, including CommonSpot, eGrail, and Ingeniux. A special bonus appendix details the role of XML in WCM, and offers a checklist for reviewing the XML capabilities of any vendor. You can buy the report online from our secure store...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/News/Article/?75</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>What Does Your CMS Call This Guy?</title>
         <description>A content management system must manage the relationships of the information objects it contains.</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/OpinionWatch/FeaturedOpinion/?feature_id=57</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>So You Want to Be in Movies</title>
         <description>EAM vendors – or for that matter, WCM, or DM companies — who think that the Entertainment Media Asset Management (EMAM) business is another untapped vertical market may find otherwise. </description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/OpinionWatch/FeaturedOpinion/?feature_id=60</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Hide Your Boss’s Golf Clubs….and Other Techniques for Evaluating WCM Packages</title>
         <description>Invite these three vendors to come in and produce a “proof-of-concept”, with each vendor installing their software on the hardware you intend it to run on.  This is the single most important step in the enterprise software selection process today.</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/OpinionWatch/FeaturedOpinion/?feature_id=62</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>The Challenges of Developing Multi-lingual Content Structures</title>
         <description>Like similar projects, we're creating a highly complex, highly organized system. But we are faced with an additional difficulty: the elements need to be multi-lingual. </description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/TopicWatch/FeaturedTopic/?feature_id=52</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Publishing Without Wires: Ready for Primetime?</title>
         <description>General consensus held that 2001 would become a year of great innovation and broader adaptation in the wireless arena, but progress has been relatively slow. </description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/TopicWatch/FeaturedTopic/?feature_id=56</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>The Case for Personal Web Publishing</title>
         <description>Dave Winer is CEO of UserLand Software, as well as the godfather of Weblogging and the SOAP protocol. </description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/PeopleWatch/FeaturedPeople/?feature_id=54</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>The Case for Digital Rights Management</title>
         <description>Bill Trippe is co-author of the new book, Digital Rights Management: Business and Technology, published by M&amp;T Books.</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/PeopleWatch/FeaturedPeople/?feature_id=55</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>What SGML Can Teach Us About XML &amp; the Web</title>
         <description>SGML vet Betty Harvey advises XML-based publishers: don't suffer the same mistakes we experienced...</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/PeopleWatch/FeaturedPeople/?feature_id=58</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>The Value of Organized Knowledge</title>
         <description>If you really want your content to be found, Jack Bryar argues, focus on building a taxonomy.</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/TopicWatch/FeaturedTopic/?feature_id=59</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Zope Content Management Framework (Part 1)</title>
         <description> In the first installment of this 2-part review, CMS veteran Adam Fields takes a look at the open-source Zope platform.</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/ProductWatch/FeaturedProduct/?feature_id=61</link>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Good Content is Difficult and Expensive to Create</title>
         <description> Author Gerry McGovern argues that too many organizations look at content as a commodity -- a kind of byproduct of their normal business processes.</description>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/Features/OpinionWatch/FeaturedOpinion/?feature_id=63</link>
      </item>
      <textinput>
         <title>Search</title>
         <description>Search all of CMSWatch</description>
         <name>q</name>
         <link>http://www.cmswatch.com/SiteSearch</link>
      </textinput>
   </channel>
</rss>
