<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document> 

<header> 
    <title>Defining Tasks</title>
    <version>0.1</version> 
    <type>Overview document</type> 
    <authors>
      <person name="Andreas Hartmann" email="andreas@apache.org"/> 
    </authors> 
</header> 
<body> 

<p>
All tasks to be used in a publication must be declared in the file
<code>[publication-directory]/content/tasks.xconf</code>.
A typical task configuration file looks like follows:
</p>
<source><![CDATA[

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tasks>

  <!-- publish page -->
  <task id="publish">
    <label>Publish</label>
    <task id="publish" class="org.lenya.cms.publishing.DefaultFilePublisher">
      <parameter name="live-path" value="content/live"/>
      <parameter name="tree-live-path" value="content/live/tree.xml"/>
    </task>
    <task id="export" class="org.lenya.cms.publishing.StaticHTMLExporter">
      <parameter name="export-path" value="resources/export/pending"/>
      <parameter name="substitute-regexp" value="s/\/lenya\/your-publication//g"/>
    </task>
  </task>
</tasks>

]]></source>
<p>
Every task must have a unique <code>id</code> attribute. This identifier is
used to address the task from the sitemap.
Every top-level task must have a child element <code>&lt;label&gt;</code>. The
content of this element is used, e. g., by the scheduler to let the user choose
a task from a list. The actual implementation of a task is identified using the
<code>class</code> attribute.
</p>

<section><title>Parameters</title>
<p>
Usually, a task needs some parameters to be executed properly.
There are two possibilities to pass parameters to a task:</p>
<ol>
  <li>
    You can define all parameters or a subset of them in the <code>tasks.xconf</code> file.
  </li>
  <li>
    The remainig parameters can be handled to the <code>TaskAction</code> or the
    <code>TaskJob</code> that executes the task. Request parameters always have a higher
    priority than parameters from the <code>tasks.xconf</code> file.
  </li>
</ol>
<p>
To simplifiy the passing of parameters to tasks, the <code>TaskAction</code> and
<code>TaskJob</code> objects create some default parameters based on
the request and session objects:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <code>Task.PARAMETER_SERVLET_CONTEXT</code> - the path of the servlet context<br/>
    <code>/home/user_id/build/jakarta-tomcat/webapps/lenya</code>
  </li>
  <li>
    <code>Task.PARAMETER_SERVER_URI</code> - the server URI<br/>
    <code>http://www.yourhost.com:8080/lenya/publication/index.html</code>
  </li>
  <li>
    <code>Task.PARAMETER_SERVER_PORT</code> - the server port<br/>
    <code>http://www.yourhost.com:8080/lenya/publication/index.html</code>
  </li>
  <li>
    <code>Task.PARAMETER_CONTEXT_PREFIX</code> - the part of the URI that precedes the publication ID<br/>
    <code>http://www.yourhost.com:8080/lenya/publication/index.html</code>
  </li>
  <li>
    <code>Task.PARAMETER_PUBLICATION_ID</code> - the publication ID<br/>
    <code>http://www.yourhost.com:8080/lenya/publication/index.html</code>
  </li>
</ul>
</section>

<section><title>Task Sequences</title>
<p>
Tasks can be nested using so-called <em>task sequences</em>. Sub-tasks of other
tasks don't need to have <code>&lt;label&gt;</code> elements because they can't
be addressed independently. Whenever a task sequence is executed, all sub-tasks
are executed in the same order as they are declared.
</p>
<p>
When you group tasks, the enclosing <code>&lt;task&gt;</code> element does not
need a <code>&lt;class&gt;</code> attribute. If you omit it, the <code>TaskSequence</code>
class is used as default. If you want to implement your own task grouping
mechanism using a subclass of <code>TaskSequence</code>, you can append a
class attribute.
</p>
<p>
All parameters that are passed to a TaskSequence are forwarded to all tasks
in the sequence. By creating a subclass of <code>TaskSequence</code> you could implement
a parameter selection mechanism, e. g. using namespace prefixes.
</p>
</section>

<section><title>Assigning Tasks to Document Types</title>
<p>
Every document type can support a set of tasks. The labels of these tasks
are displayed on the scheduler screen of a document of this type.
To assign a task to a document type, you have to edit the file
<code>[publication-directory]/config/doctypes/doctypes.xconf</code>:
</p>
<source><![CDATA[

<doctypes>
  <doc type="Simple-Document">
    <tasks>
      <task id="publish"/>
      <task id="backup"/>
      ...
    </tasks>
  </doc>
  ...
</doctypes>

]]></source>
<p>
You can associate every task with an arbitrary number of document types.
</p>

</section>


</body>
</document>