<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!-- $Id: index.xml 43150 2004-07-27 19:41:17Z thorsten $ -->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "document-v12.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>The Apache Lenya Community</title>
    <version/>
    <type/>
  </header>
  <body>
	<p>
		Here you will find information on how to interact with and become a member 
		of the Apache Lenya community. Please read as well <link href="ext:forrest.contrib">Contributing to Apache Forrest</link> 
    from the forrest community because it contains some more information about the process.
	</p>

  <section>
    <title>Contribute to the Wiki</title>
    <p>The <link href="ext:wiki/lenya">Lenya Wiki</link> is the scratchpad for the
    Lenya documentation as well as a kind of whiteboard that is used by the community
    to sketch proposals about the further direction of the project.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
	<title>Contribute code</title>
  <note>Please use our <link href="site:issue.add">Bug tracker</link> to submit patches instead of sending them to the mailing list. 
    All our committer started in creating an account here. ;-)<br/>
    
    </note>
	<p>
		You can contribute code as patch via our <link href="site:issue.add">Bug tracker</link>. 
		For this, you file a bug entry in Bugzilla, using the links provided below. 
		The bug entries in Bugzilla should provide a description of what the patch does, 
		and how to apply it. Any further discussion should occur on the Lenya Developer list (see <link href="site:ml">mailing lists</link>)
	</p>
	<section>
		<title>Preparing a Patch</title>
			<ul>
				<li>For general procedures please see the Cocoon documentation <link href="site:cocoon.howto.patch">How to Prepare a Patch</link> and 
          <link href="site:cocoon.howto.bugzilla">How to Contribute a Patch via Bugzilla</link>. 
          Note that the actual command to create the patch is <code>svn diff</code> (instead of <code>cvs diff -u</code> as 
          suggested in said documents).</li>
				<li>Make sure you follow the <link href="site:coding">coding guidelines</link>.</li>
				<li>Test your patch by applying it to a fresh checkout of Lenya. In Eclipse for instance, this is done by choosing "apply patch" in the team perspective.</li>
				<li>Follow this link to enter your patch in Bugzilla: <link href="site:issue.add">add a new patch</link>.</li>
			</ul>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Apply open patches</title>
		<p>
			If you as committer feel that you have some spare time, here is a list of open issues.
			Just go ahead fix them ;-).
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li><link href="ext:issues.open.bugs.enhancement">list of all provided enhancement bugs</link></li>
			<li><link href="ext:issues.open.patches">list of all provided patches</link></li>
		</ul>
	</section>
</section>
  </body>
</document>
